hello and welcome
it's July 17 2023. we're here in active
inference math stream number 5.1 with
Chris Bodner on topological deep
learning graphs complexes and sheaves so
thank you for joining Chris looking
forward to your presentation and
discussion
yeah thanks thanks all for uh having me
so yeah as I was just saying
um this is um my my PhD pieces which
I've finished a couple of months ago
it's also kind of a public online so you
know if you want to go into the details
just kind of look this up on the
internet and uh you should be able to
find it easily uh obviously there's lots
of stuff in there so I kind of try to
give an overview uh today and maybe also
go in a little bit more detail in
certain aspects
um since there's you know not a lot of
time to go through everything
um
so yeah now I'm on my Microsoft research
so this is some basically all work that
I did in the past then when I was at the
University of Cambridge
um all right so let's let's get uh
started
um right so let's let's start very
easily
um now I'm actually not sure exactly
what's kind of the background of the
people who are watching uh but uh in
machine learning there's uh there's all
these kind of subfield that emerged a
few years ago which is called geometric
deep learning
um
which is essentially looking at how to
apply this kind of deep learning neural
network architectures on data living on
all sorts of
um
you know kind of structures or
geometries or or spaces if you want
um and this has a lot of applications
especially in the Life Sciences and
there's kind of been a lot of instances
of this in kind of you know very famous
Publications and all which you see here
but you know just to give some examples
for instance if you if you have proteins
or molecules or things like that they
usually represent it as graphs
um and you kind of have some data living
on these graphs like kind of the
properties of certain atoms and and so
on
um so so these kind of things
um and so far this kind of
um
species or this kind of problems
learning problems if you want they have
been approached mostly kind of with a
geometrical mindset as the kind of name
of the of the subfield
um also mentions
um but
um something that you know I would argue
is that geometry is not everything that
you need and there's kind of other
non-geometrical aspects when you are in
such a setting
um
and this is kind of quite obvious once
you realize that the spaces that kind of
show up in in the field and in many
applications uh they are very
heterogeneous so as I mentioned for
instance you could have graphs that you
know could represent anything in this
case it's the caffeine molecule that you
see here on the left and you want to you
know have some models that predict
certain properties of this molecule and
so on uh but for instance you can have
grits and we see grids all the time and
data living on grades and I'm referring
to images videos they are all kind of
you know pixels living on a grid
um and then you can have more
sophisticated things you could have some
meshes for instance uh they're all over
in computer graphics and then you could
have some sort of manifold so for
instance if you're doing maybe weather
modeling or something you you know we
live on a sphere topologically speaking
um so you might want to model your data
as living on a fear and and so on
um
but nonetheless uh even if these places
are kind of
geometrically kind of heterogeneous and
some of them not don't even have a
geometrical structure in kind of a
strict mathematical sense they all have
What's called the topological structure
which is kind of like kind of a weaker
kind of structure uh but it's it's kind
of more General
um and I'm going to talk a bit uh in a
few seconds about what that means but in
general you do kind of mathematical
physics you kind of have a ladder of
structures where kind of uh you know you
kind of keep building on top and the
more structure you have the more
sophisticated things you can do and so
on and you know at the basis of this
diagram just have sets it's just kind of
a collection of elements with no kind of
extra structure uh and then you kind of
keep going up in this uh leather and you
you add stop stop on top of sets and so
on
um and as I was saying kind of most of
the work is kind of focused on maybe the
top levels of this hierarchy but it's
kind of topological level it's a kind of
uh you know the weakest kind of level
you can add on top of that has kind of
been neglected to a large extent
um and part of what I've been doing in
my PhD thesis was essentially looking at
this kind of learning problems on these
kind of spaces from a more topological
perspective and you know kind of Fight
The Filling uh these blanks
um so this is kind of the overview and
now okay so if we are to adopt this
topological perspective what would that
actually mean or how would that look
like
um I guess it could look in different
ways but in what I've done in my faces
it looks kind of like this so we have
horizontally we kind of have a space
um that could be anything it's just kind
of an abstract space you know could be a
grid or things like we've seen uh in the
previous example and kind of vertically
attached to the regions of the space we
have data
um so data is kind of this vertical
component and you kind of see these uh
Flags kind of being you know kind of
anchored in these regions so that kind
of signifies you have some data that's
kind of associated with that region
um so that's kind of the high level
perspective
um and I'm going to make that a bit more
concrete a bit later
um and there's kind of two essential
things about this picture
uh first thing is locality so the data
is uh attached to some regions of this
space this topological space
um and and in that sense it's local so
it's kind of associated with the region
and maybe to give a concrete example if
you kind of have a temperature sensor
somewhere in space right you could think
of whatever that sensor is measuring is
kind of a property of kind of the
immediate surrounding of of you know
around that sensor so it's kind of
describing some property of of a region
in space
um so so that'll be kind of a good
example
um and another kind of Axiom uh that
that uh we're starting with is that
um the space has structure
um so the space has kind of it's kind of
made up of various regions and these
regions intersect in various ways
um
so the and and that implicitly also
makes our data structure because the
data is attached to these regions so so
there is kind of some some structure in
in the data
um all right so that's kind of the
picture and actually many of these
things relate to category Theory I'm not
gonna go in depth into this because it's
kind of sophisticated and I'm not an
expert myself in category Theory
um but kind of the the high level here
is that category theory is kind of a
nice way to uh translate between
different structure in mathematics and
kind of you know discuss about
properties of certain kinds of objects
and translate that to some different
kinds of objects and find all these kind
of relations and connections and a
concrete example is for instance if you
want to study some manifolds on surfaces
you could associate some groups to these
surfaces and then any sorts of relations
between this kind of surfaces also
translating some relations about these
groups or some other algebraic
structures so you could study these
manifolds by doing algebra instead of
doing you know geometry or topology or
something else
um so also in this case this kind of
manifests in the fact that we kind of
translate these
um from spaces to data so kind of
because we associate the regions in in a
space certain kinds of data this is kind
of how these translation manifests in in
what I've just described in the previous
picture so you could think of this as
some sort of translation or mapping from
from spaces and regions in that space to
kind of data attached to that space
um but yeah I'm not going to go in a lot
of detail into this but it's just kind
of to you know to keep in the back of
your mind
um that there's there's this stuff
lurking in the background
um all right so this is I I promise this
is the early math definition I'm giving
in this talk and then and then I'll stop
um but just because I'm mentioned in
topological space spaces quite often I
just wanted to kind of
um give this axiomatic definition
um which might sound sophisticated but I
have a picture at the end and hopefully
it'll be clear
um so yeah so what is it um so it's just
a set as I was saying we start with set
and we put stuff on top right so you
start with a set and then you also have
a collection of subsets of this set
um called the open sets that need to
satisfy a certain axioms so you could
think of these open settings kind of
regions of the space very informally
speaking
um so something that uh kind of has to
be satisfied is that well the empty set
and the set itself
um need to be open set so in in some
sense you could think of this as saying
the set itself is a region of that space
uh very informally
um which you know it's a kind of uh say
obvious and then there's some some
kind of constraints about intersecting
and taking units of this region so uh if
we take the intersection of two regions
we should get another one of these
regions
um and if we take a union of these
regions we should take we should get
another region
um and uh there is some constraints
again like okay how big this
intersection should be there should be
finite intersections but you could have
infinite unions but that's a
technicality and we can just skip
anyways but to see a picture so on the
left you just see the set X itself and
here I put like a potential neighborhood
structure kind of like open set
structure on this space so we have an
open set here another open set V by this
Axiom the intersections would also be an
open set so yes it is intersection in
the middle being another opposite and
then the set itself is another open set
so it's just kind of a splitting stuff
into regions kind of
um you could think of it like that
um all right so so this is this is a top
logical space
um and now let's add data right so we
we mentioned that we have data and then
we put we sorry we have a space and then
we add data on top uh so so far we've
seen how a topological space looks like
now let's add this kind of vertical
stuff these flags that you saw before we
we just put some data on top of these
regions
um and if we put data on all the regions
of the space on all the open sets
um we get these uh
structures that in categories here like
in algebraic topology also geometry they
are called pre-shapes
um which which sounds very fancy but all
it's just kind of a definition of uh
what I was already describing is
actually you have some data for each
region these these F of so for instance
for uh bridge and U you have this F of U
which is kind of the data attached to
region you so you can think of f of U
some some set with with describing the
data that lives there in that region
um but there's also an extra thing you
you have some some sort of maps going
between these kind of uh pieces of data
um and these are called restriction maps
and and why is that it's kind of they
provide you a way to uh kind of zoom in
if you want right like you have you have
the data attached to the whole set X and
then you could think okay how do I take
this data how do I go from this data to
data on a smaller region on on X so it's
kind of a way to zoom in on that data in
uh essentially and I'm going to show
some some example in a second so these
are called
um preaches and just to see an example
our space here is kind of one of the
simplest kind of space you could think
of just 1D or horizontal line right this
is the real line
um and then you have some regions which
are just given by open intervals uh on
on these uh
uh yeah on the Via line and then some
pieces of data could be functions like
continuous functions on on those regions
so here is like some sample data on on
this first interval here's another
function on the second interval here's
some data on this third interval and
actually in this case it happens that
all these
um functions agree on the overlap so
where these regions overlap they take
the same values and we can actually glue
them together on a single uh in a single
function over the entire region right so
so this is just an example of
um of a pre-shift and it's called the
pre-shift of continuous functions
um so our data in this case is
continuous functions and the space is
just the real line
um and we put these functions on top to
realign
um and but it turns out because of this
kind of special property uh that we can
kind of glue data and we uniquely get
some other piece of data right we we can
take these three pieces it's just
exactly like a like a puzzle right we
put this thing through things together
and we get a fourth thing which is kind
of a single function uh where we just
overlapped these these functions right
um and
uh these uh appreciates that satisfy
this kind of properties where you can
kind of glue them to get a unique piece
of data they are called sheaves
um and uh basically the pre-shift of
continuous functions is actually a shift
um so this is kind of a way to formalize
data attached to these things
um it's gonna get less technical in a
second
um so just to give more examples so for
instance in this way we could describe
data on a sphere and let's say if this
data is just some Vector field on this
here so let's see if this is earth right
this could be some wind Vector field
right like if we do weather modeling or
something you just have a vector field
describing the wind on on the surface of
Earth right
um and you might want to do some machine
learning on top of this where this kind
of vector field has a sheath structure
and you could think of it as a chief
because you know if you have like some
Vector field on the red region a vector
field on the yellow region I can kind of
glued them together uniquely if they
overlap if they agree on the overlap and
we get the vector field on this bigger
region but something that's quite nice
is that even if we have a very very
different kind of space namely a graph
which is very different from a sphere in
in all points of view and we can still
apply the exact same kind of axioms and
terminology and and kind of definitions
and we can have a shift over a graph so
in this way we could have for instance
some features Associated to the nodes of
the ground some features associated with
the edges of the graph and there's
another node which has its own features
and this is actually the exact same
thing we have in graph machine learning
um so this is quite nice for this kind
of topological perspective allows us to
do is you know we we kind of have a
unified way of thinking if you want
about very kind of heterogeneous spaces
and we can model on all of them data
attached to them by using this kind of
shift terminology and other ways as well
but I'm not going to that in this talk
um all right so this is kind of an
overview of what I've been doing in my
thesis
um and just to kind of dive a bit deeper
into this
um I just yeah I wanted to go in uh into
one paper that we did at Europe's uh
last year yeah so this was last year
um on uh what's called shift diffusion
so essentially how can we use what I've
just described to do some useful stuff
when doing machine learning on graphs
um all right and this was a
collaboration with Francisco de Giovanni
but in Chamberlain uh Pietro Leo my
advisor and Michael bronstein
um okay so before I dive into this I
just want to give some background in
case people are not familiar with this
um so the kind of
favorite architecture of people doing
machine learning on graphs these days
are these things called graph neural
networks
um which are actually very simple kind
of models so
in this setting you you have some
features so each node in your graph will
have some features this is what is h
Vector here denote so it's
um the vector H associated with node a
at layer or time D whatever so you have
some features for each of these nodes
and what you're doing each of if you are
at a certain note you want to kind of
compute a new representation or a new
new features for for this now that the
next layer
um
so since you're learning representations
um and what the graphene networks are
doing this node will receive a message
from all the other
nodes that our neighbors with this node
um and this these uh message can also be
passed you know can use on neural
networks in there but essentially some
processing of these features of the
neighbors and these are aggregated into
this message so here in in green
um and then there is this is passed
through some update function
um that combines the message from the
neighbors with the old representation of
this node and it gives you a new
representation kind of the next layer
um and this happens for all the nodes
right so then you get some new
representations for this node and this
is one layer and then you kind of keep
repeating this for as many layers as you
like
um so this is kind of how you do deep
learning on on graphs
um it's kind of a very very simple uh
recipe and most models actually vary in
the way they kind of compute these
messages messages and in the way these
update function is designed uh but
that's kind of the parameter is the most
of these models use otherwise they all
kind of respect this framework and work
in this kind of particular way
um and to give you maybe an example for
why you would want to do this
uh you might want to do note
classification this is kind of a classic
problem in graph machine learning there
are others but I'm just going to talk
about this because it's easier
um so you have a graph and this graph
um has nodes that have different labels
here there's just two kinds of labels
these orange and and blue
um
and you you have some edges between uh
these nodes and what you want is you
want to do this kind of a message
passing that I was describing to compute
some representations for these nodes
where you can easily classify you can
easily classify the blue and the orange
notes
um now something that's quite
interesting is that for many kind of
graph neural networks
um
depending on the properties of these
graphs and how these kind of different
nodes are connected their performance
might vary quite a lot
um so in particular they're affected by
this property called heterophili
um so this kind of a measure of how much
uh opposites attractive you want right
so uh it has a very simple formula
um basically you take the number of
edges between orange and blue notes and
you divide by the total number of edges
right so so basically you kind of check
how many connections we have in this
graph between things that are quite you
know they are opposite to each other
versus you know connections that are
between similar kind of nodes
um so if you have this kind of a lot of
these kind of heterogeneous connections
then you have very high heteropoly
um and it turns out that many Graphics
are not exactly struggle in that setting
it's very hard to to classify things in
that setting
um and iteratively you could kind of
also you know figure out why because you
know you you could easily apply to some
kind of reasoning where you know oh this
note looks a lot like these other node
is connected to so they kind of must be
in you know in the same Community if you
want or in the same label but it's much
harder to do that when you know all
things are kind of different from
um from each other
um and and this community is kind of
don't form right even visually if you if
you see a graph and it has a nicely
clustered communities you know it's
quite easy to draw a line between those
and say oh this is uh communities
another Community but if things are very
mixed
um then it's quite challenging and it
turns out it's also challenging for
these models uh not just for kind of our
intuition when when you know we would
have to do this
um so this is kind of some problem where
um this perspective this topological
perspective I was mentioning uh will be
used to to you know do some useful stuff
um
okay so coming back to toshibs on graph
um and at this point I think you can
largely forget what I mentioned in your
introduction uh or if there's something
give misunderstood there uh you know we
kind of start from zero bit here so
um there's no problem so
on the left
um you just have a graph
um which is kind of the incident
structure of a graph I just don't hear
the simplest possible graph that has two
nodes V and U and then there's an edge
between them so this is just a graph
with one Edge then that's all that's
going on here and I've just represented
it by kind of in this kind of incidence
structure kind of way right node V is
incident to node e and node uh sorry
Edge e and node U is incident to h e so
this is just an incident structure and
what is kind of triangle symbol we're
showing is just these incidence
structure is just the way to symbolize
this incidence relation if you want
um okay so this is just a graph right
and a way we can kind of think of of
fields on graphs is just mapping these
graph structures so this is kind of this
categorical Theory translation we
translate this graph into something else
which looks you know very similar the
structure is kind of the same it's just
kind of the meaning of these uh things
change so for each node V we have
um here this will be a vector space so F
of e is a vector space for each node
here we have F of U which is another
Vector space uh for each Edge e we have
this Fe which is another Vector space
um so all nodes have their own Vector
spaces and the features Associated to
those nodes leaving those Vector spaces
so basically for each node we have a
vector space of features that that's all
that's going on so far and also these
arrows that these incident relations
also translate into something and they
translate into the obvious thing linear
Maps so if these are vector spaces then
these things should be linear Maps or
just some matrices essentially right so
for each Arrow you see here we have a
matrix
and
um
uh see yeah and something uh that I'll
I'll argue and show in a few slides is
that basically message passing
um
uh is very similar on graphs it's very
similar with group actions in in group
Theory
um so let me explain exactly why so we
kind of can think of the what we have on
the left the these arrows in from the
incidence relation they could think of
these errors as kind of uh some patterns
we can press so what do I mean by that
so if we have this node V on the left
right and this e now if we have some
features some feature living in fov
right we could just kind of press this
arrow button here and then if we
multiply this matrix by this feature we
will get an edge feature
um so it's kind of like
um if you go along this Arrow this
Matrix will multiply this feature and
this vertex feature and it will give you
an edge feature
um so if you think of these arrows as
kind of giving you some sort of actions
that you can play with to move features
from vertex to Edge and and Edge to
vertex so in this case it's kind of a
left action right so this is what I'm
saying I'm taking this R which is uh
this one here and I act on some features
of node V so this HOV that lives here
right
um and how I do that is I just take this
Matrix this Matrix associated with this
arrow and I multiply this Vector HOV so
just Matrix times Vector that's all and
then we get an edge feature so this is
just kind of a way to to move from here
to here so this already kind of looks a
bit like message passing right we're
kind of passing a message from this
vertex to this Edge
um but now we also need to pass a
message from this Edge to these other
vertex used so we kind of you know we
need to get from V to U
um so and we did that by passing through
e so by doing that we could do that by
kind of going in reverse so we could
have a right accent
um where instead of applying this Matrix
we applied adjoint Matrix so it doesn't
the transpose Matrix so in instead if we
want to go from here to here
um instead of applying this Matrix we
apply its transpose because we want to
go the other way around
um so this is this is a if we compose
these things then we can move features
from V to U so this is just the way
uh that kind of we can apply these
actions uh to to do message passing and
these are called shift actions or
pre-shift actions and uh I'm gonna now
say what's kind of the relation with
between this and what we have in group
uh Theory
um so one way to
represent the group is by kind of having
some sort of graph
um like here on on the left so
uh we kind of have some star object it
is just kind of a dummy thing there uh
but all the group structure is in these
arrows right so for each group element
so let's say this G is a 90 degree
rotation for instance that that's uh
let's say we do have a group of
rotations that just to have some
concrete example these uh
so these Arrow could correspond to a 90
degree rotation we have another arrow
that does the opposite minus kind of 90
degree rotation that's the inverse of
that transformation
um so this is kind of the structure of
this group and if we have we also do
this kind of similar kind of translation
as we've just seen
um so basic basically we Define a
pre-shift on this group uh we map this
star to a vector space so the star kind
of replace is the vertex uh we had
before now we just have a single vertex
uh and it's just these arrows we have um
so the star is not this Vector space
that you showed here in in blue right
um and now if we actually do group
actions which are kind of a very well
established Concept in group Theory
um
well for instance if you want to act on
this vertex oh sorry not vertex on this
vector v right here you have a vector in
this Vector space and you want to act on
it by this group transformation G so
essentially you want to press this Arrow
so you you apply some action on it
um then what you do is well because of
this translation this G has been mapped
to some Matrix which is the rotation
Matrix the corresponding rotation Matrix
and you apply this rotation Matrix on V
and you get like a 90 degree rotation
here
um so this is what what's going on this
kind of vertical Vector is showing the
rotated Vector
um
so this is completely analogous with
what we've seen on the previous slide
um is uh this is how kind of chiefs
connect these kind of actions so
essentially what you could think of as
message passing is same as group actions
in group Theory but you just replace
this group with a graph so it's kind of
analogous to that right so uh it's just
kind of a different kind of translations
where we replace the object on the left
uh now it looks like this is a graph
this is a group right so but kind of the
rest stays exactly the same so
um you could and this kind of gives us a
way to formalize in a way by looking in
this topological perspective to connect
all these kind of symmetries and things
like that that have been explored quite
a lot in machine learning through
message passing on graphs and to see one
way in which in which they are related
um okay so now in my circuit this was
all very sophistically and nice but you
know what what is this going anywhere
basically
um and I'm just going to show you kind
of a very forward example there there's
more about you know the time is limited
um and something we we showed is that
uh as I was saying in the beginning many
graphene networks kind of struggle in
these heterophilic graphs and what we've
shown is that
um no matter how heterophilic or kind of
weird your your graph is uh you can
always kind of find some shift structure
essentially kind of a message passing
neural network that
if you use sufficient layers it will be
able to disentangle the classes of the
of the nodes right so just to show you
in this picture what you have here on
the very far left
um the colors of the notes they they
show the clasp so we have three there's
three colors here so three classes right
um and this is kind of the graph in the
beginning and the position of the nodes
in this box denotes the features so
that's a way to kind of just to
visualize the features
um the the position the 2D position is
actually the 2D feature Vector of each
node
um and you can see in the beginning
everything is kind of super messy and
entangled right like if you want to
classify these notes it's kind of very
hard because the representations the
initial representations are are very
messy and kind of uh intertwined
um but as we stack more layers of a
particular kind of key for a message
passing model
um you see how progressively these
classes get you know kind of more decent
angle and more
at each new layer and so that kind of
this representations kind of collapse
and they form this kind of clusterings
right and then when you get with
something like at the end you can kind
of see these three communities very
clearly and it's extremely easy to
separate
um and kind of the essence behind this
results was we we showed for different
kinds of problems what sorts of Chief or
message passing models you need by using
the theory to solve kind of problems and
um this is quite important because it
kind of shows you some important bits
and pieces in the architecture that you
might want to to kind of change or or
use in order to solve certain kinds of
problems and we also had some sort of
impossibility results so if you use a
graphing a network of some kind you
can't solve this problem or you'll
struggle to solve this problem and we
also saw okay if you use some more
general ones then you might have a
chance
so this is kind of some the you know
high level view behind
um these theoretical stuff
um and what we're actually doing in
practice
um is to essentially learn these message
passing functions or to learn the sheet
or these matrices so in in practice like
when someone gives you a node
classification tasks is very hard to
know beforehand what what exactly is the
right
um the right C for the right message
passing model uh to sort that task
um and what we do is actually we learn
that from data so we learned these
matrices that do the message passing we
learn them from data
um by passing some using some neural
networks which are shown here in red
um and and then you learn how to kind of
transfer features between these Vector
spaces and kind of move them around so
this is just showing how these vectors
which are features of these nodes and
edges how they kind of moved around by
depends going through the Via this
matrices just some Matrix
multiplications
um
and okay so so that's kind of a high
level here behind this model and we
evaluated this on some kind of real
world uh heterophilic data sets
um uh where you you have to classify
nodes based on kind of various
communities or different kinds of labels
and these data sets going from
um right to left they are getting more
heterophilic so in some sense more
challenging for classic architectures
and our models which are kind of
inspired by all this stuff the dimension
they score quite highly in in these
benchmarks
um and at the same time they also
revealed some or Justified some various
choices that other models in this space
have done but maybe they were not so
well Justified or maybe they had
different kind of motivations we also
managed to kind of show why various
things they were already doing why they
made sense from from the point of view
of this kind of uh Theory
um all right well that's it's all um all
I had
um yeah thanks for for listening and
yeah happy to chat more about this and
also have lots of backup slides in case
you know uh depending on how far away
you can Venture offer with these
questions
oh well awesome work thank you for the
presentation
for people who are in the live chat they
can write some questions but there's
many things I think we could talk about
so I want to start with reading a quote
from an abstract of the paper by
uh vanderlar kudal and DeVries just to
kind of ground this in the active
inference context and and really justify
why the message passing approaches that
you are describing are helping in the
active inference modeling so the paper
it's two papers it's called realizing
synthetic active inference agents and
they wrote with a full message passing
account of synthetic active inference
agents it becomes possible to derive and
reuse message updates across models and
move closer to Industrial applications
of synthetic active inference framework
so how does knowing the message passing
structure
help reuse a model across different
settings or like facilitate the
legibility of the model
right um so first of all I'm not super
familiar with the kind of active
inference literature
um so
you know you'll have to help me there a
bit in in for for to Anchor maybe the
discussions a bit more into that
um but I think if I understand correctly
the the kind of question uh you're
you're getting at is basically how how
can kind of message passing help us
generalize you know in kind of various
kinds of settings or maybe you know from
one graph to another and and things like
that and
um these these isn't kind of active area
of of research how exactly this
generalization is happening
um but something you could notice where
is something that
um for instance was shown like these
models are quite good at for instance
plotting patterns or structures uh
depending on how exactly you implement
them but for instance uh you know let's
say you have a triangle in your graph or
you know that'll be kind of a simple
structure right you you have a triangle
or some other kind of kind of Gadgets in
your in your graph like particular
subgraphs right that might show up in in
different kinds of uh you know various
graphs the graphs themselves might look
completely different from each other but
these kind of patterns might kind of be
re-emerging in multiple like local
patterns like three emerging multiple
graphs and that could help your way to
kind of generalize right like you could
see for instance if you have clicks
they're super important and kind of when
you do social network modeling and
things like that because they kind of
show this kind of um you know close
group of friends right they all talk to
each other so they can form a click like
everyone's connected to each other right
and then you you might be able to use
that in general if another completely
different social context
um where you know the these agents are
again kind of communicating in a similar
manner or connected in a similar manner
even if the kind of overall pattern is
quite different
um and it goes Way Beyond just kind of
structural similarities because there's
also features in there so there's
combinations of kind of structural
patterns and features that you know give
your even more complicated patterns
right like you might have a triangle but
then also two of the features in this
triangle are you know look in a certain
way and one that looks in another way so
so that gives you even more kind of
refinement then and uh you know even
kind of richer pattern detection
abilities
um so so you have essentially this you
know ability to kind of spot spot
patterns at multiple scales as well so
you could see this happening at in
multiple skills you could have patterns
of patterns right you could have uh
Community entire communities connected
in various patterns and so on
um and again it's kind of also research
question how do you capture these
hierarchical patterns and so on
um you know in general you have to do
more message passing if you want to
capture things that are further away
from each other because otherwise they
can't talk to each other right
um so yeah I don't know if that that
actually answered your question or if I
was kind of going in the right direction
there
oh it's great it brings up a lot of
different cool ideas like like this
patterns all the way down but totally
agree I I think we can now
perhaps explore some more specific
connections to active inference because
hopefully the the
um listenership or viewership of this
it's kind of like a two-way street like
some people may be coming from more of
your background and then learning about
active inference and generative models
as a specific system of Interest the
first time but also certainly for a lot
of people in the active inference space
like these methods coming from category
Theory have only recently come up
to I guess more prominence in Bayesian
modeling at least where we are so it's
kind of it's a cool connection making
yeah um I think one of the biggest touch
points off the bat was like you
mentioned multiplying a matrix by a
vector and interpreting that as an edge
so just in the in the inference part of
the generative model of about sensory
observations we always talk about the
thermometer observation and then the
underlying hidden State temperature
so that like exactly describes that case
and that's why we can represent the
active inference generative models the
perceptual parts and the action Parts in
terms of matrix multiplication it's why
the Matlab code for generative models
does look mostly like matrix
multiplication and it can all be done
explicitly that way so
how does that feed like are there models
that don't have this feature
or what do we gain by having like all of
our edges defined as
um appreciative action with a matrix and
a vector
in this setting of agent generative
models with perception and action
like once yeah yeah any thoughts on that
yeah I think
essentially kind of the the graph
structure is kind of telling you these
things interacting in some way right so
um there there's some communication
between these vertices if you you know
if we're kind of in a graph setting
right
um and then kind of what the Sheikh is
giving you or or any message passive
model essentially is is expressing a way
that in which way that connection should
manifest in the model or in what way
that connection should be used to
process information
um so in this case I was mentioning okay
we you have like linear Maps because you
could go on the type if your type of
data or vector spaces then this
transformation will be some sort of
linear Maps
um
but it doesn't necessarily have to be so
for instance it could go to any
nonlinear transformation right like if
and this is what's happening in general
in practice
um you know if you if you have a
neighbor the message coming from that
neighbor could be modulated by any sort
of transformation you you want so it
could be linear it could be non-linear
it could be
something I don't know you you can
specify it basically uh but essentially
you could think of this as
you have a structure level telling you
who should communicate to whom
um and then you kind of have some
semantics that is kind of shift is
adding on top uh saying how should these
things communicate right like the first
thing is uh who should communicate or
what should communicate and and then the
semantics we had on top essentially
describe uh how should that
communication uh manifest uh essentially
very cool I think that Maps like exactly
to how we talk about the sparsity of
variables in degenerative model
so here the topology of the nodes in the
graph that we want to do message passing
on are going to be describing like the
agent and the environment or like the
generative model that includes
perception cognition and action it's a
lot of people have proposed different
sparsity architectures for integrated
modeling of perception cognition action
so one example would just be like kind
of Around the Clock like action
influences environment environment
influences perception back to cognition
you could add a self Loop
blanket and different kinds of
connectivities and that defines the
sparsity topologically which is where
you showed the stack and and you were on
the second and the third levels I think
of the stack and then like What flows
it has to be described how it actually
what that edge does so what what is that
what is that that is also being provided
yeah yeah exactly and it could even go
to the extreme where you know does that
edge actually do anything so for
instance if you uh have a matrix that's
just the zero Matrix for instance
Associated to that edge you're just
going to multiply by zero or an item
that gives you zero and it's kind of
essentially pruning that edge right like
I can't get rid of it I don't want that
communication to happen but there's kind
of there's also kind of this possibility
where these kind of semantics they
override the structural level where you
say okay I don't need to communicate you
know with this other agent person or
whatever it depends on what this
vertices actually mean and in what
context in what context you are and then
there's also the case where you could do
some sort of selective pruning where
um these Matrix depending on
um so in in kind of linear algebra The
Matrix has a kernel so it's uh all the
stuff that that Matrix sense to zero so
what vectors are sent to zero right but
not everything will be sent to zero
unless you're the zero Matrix
so depending on the features of the
neighbors you could also just send some
of the neighbors to zero right and that
kind of removes those Neighbors From the
equation they just kind of get you know
you you yeah they're not they're not
factored in anymore so you kind of have
this you know it's a way to get the
sparsity I guess that that they were
also talking about uh
where you know certain only maybe a
small subset of the inputs or kind of uh
yeah only a a subset of the features are
actually kind of doing some meaningful
stuff among the neighbors and everything
else will be kind of zeroed up
yeah that makes me think of the lasso
regression which tries to set most
variables of having an impact of zero so
that a few hopefully important variables
really pop out in the analysis but also
there's there's newer techniques I guess
of attention modeling and maybe waiting
that isn't just like okay set five of
them to one and then the rest and then
the rest of them to zero like more
nuanced um so I think that sparsity with
the expressivity is basically the The
Best of Both Worlds because you do want
to have a situation where there is an
edge but the attention being paid to it
is zero so functionally
that doesn't have an update on the
belief State even though the in
principle The Edge exists
and that's why we can model situations
where like the
agent believes they have impact in the
world but actually just because the edge
in principle exists doesn't mean that it
has any given impact and so that allows
like the articulation of these models
where they factorize and keeps
interpretable motifs in terms of just
Little clusters
of uh motifs here in our case describing
the action perception and cognition
types of systems of interest but people
I believe already implicitly do this
um like they will often add an adjective
and refer to X kind of active inference
so like deep active inference with a
temporal Horizon sophisticated active
inference with this kind of nesting
and those are pointing to a given
feature but of course those features
as we're hoping should be composable
and so
this seems to be bringing
tools that are even more General than
just action perception modeling
because they're at a lower level of
abstraction than like any specific
system of interest but where this work
and kind of Timeless thinking around
cybernetic systems
come together through the active inverse
generative model as a base graph
it gets very exciting
yeah yeah and maybe it's also something
we're emphasizing here is that even if
this kind of semantic level can can get
rid of some edges right by doing this
kind of pruning something it cannot get
rid of is the computation so something
that kind of that
structural graph level forces you to do
it kind of tells you what should you
spend compute time on right because like
if
even if you're going to decide to prune
an edge you still need to decide that
which you know takes compute time so you
still need to look at all your neighbors
if you are not right and and decide what
to prove in or maybe you're done print
anything or whatever but you have to
look at every Edge and one way to look
at this is uh the kind of the graph
structure defines your computational
graph or kind of a computational yeah a
series of computational steps you have
to execute and then the kind of the
shift structure or the message passing
model actually specifies what those
steps are and you know in one particular
way they they look exactly
um and so yeah that's one point and yeah
you also mentioned attention and
actually
yeah I'm glad you did because this is
actually quite related and in in certain
ways more General than attention and
actually maybe going back to this slide
it might be a nice way to
um to see this so here basically what
happens in attention
um instead of learning these matrices
that we learned here uh in attention you
learn attention coefficients here so
just learn a scalar that's the attention
coefficient how much attention should I
pay to essentially well you know this
overall Edge let's say which will be
just a scalar what we do is kind of a
bit more complicated because you just
learn how do I transform these neighbors
so it's kind of a whole Matrix rather
than a single scalar
uh but there's also some subtle
differences but in in a in a follow-up
work we did we also combined this with
with attention and and went a bit more
General and
um that that also worked uh quite well
but the kind of underlying idea is is
very similar you want to modulate the
way it transform information based on
the information itself right so we have
this kind of one level of
um recursivity if you want or kind of
yeah that we're also alluding to in that
you know it happens in active inference
where okay you're you're so if I'm not V
right my neighbor you it has some
features and based on these features
which are XU I'm gonna find out the
Matrix that will be used to process X
here right so it's kind of very
recursive and it's what happens with
attention right based on the features of
node U I'm gonna compute an attention
coefficient that I'm going to apply to
this feature over here right I'm gonna
decide based on this feature how much
attention should I pay to it
um and here we decide how should I
process it more generally uh in a linear
way
um so you have this kind of loopiness
structure embedded in there
awesome all
bring up a few more points because I
think there's there's so many great
pieces so Toby
Sinclair Smythe who we recently
discussed his dissertation in live
stream 54.
introduced a term or Lisa phrasing the
compositional cognitive cartography and
so thinking about the compositionality
of cognitive systems
and I think what you're describing here
with this notion that the mappings are
more General than
the kind of attention mechanisms known
famously today that those represent like
a lower dimensional special case of one
kind of architecture
makes me think about how
the Bayesian graph is kind of semantic
in principle
and can have all of these nice
categorical formalisms around them but
then
and and you can even build the connector
to empirical data with the pre-shief and
the Sheaf which may be news to even many
empirical researchers doing data
analysis certainly was for me but the
message passing provides a rigorous
translation from whatever semantic model
is proposed topologically
to an implementation procedure that can
be planned for
and executed in linear time or at least
with definable characteristics so
message passing plays a really important
part in going from like the abstract
what is possible to the implementations
of any of these actual models and it
does it in a really General way where is
it accurate to say that we hope that
implementation
with message passing compatible
generative models will kind of roll out
better
because we won't have some of the
engineering challenges that less
reusable
abstractions might carry
it's it's hard to say I think there
there's also certainly some limitations
to this paradigm
as well so just kind of doing this kind
of message passing things you were
mentioning one thing is that it kind of
scales up uh quite easily like linearly
with the size of the graph but that also
come at the cost so there is certain
results showing this has limit in
expressivity
um so if you actually want to to
go beyond this for instance you have to
instead of just looking at pairs of
nodes you have to look at tuples and and
this kind of high order uh groupings of
nodes
um in in order to kind of get higher
exclusivity there's all sorts of
techniques to do that
um but yeah and there's always this kind
of tension between
being more expressive and being
efficient that you know will always be
there in any sort of algorithm or or
method
um
so so it's kind of hard to say I mean
it's definitely we can definitely say
this is kind of not the ultimate
solution let's say if you want to do
things message passing in itself you
know but you know maybe doing some sort
of computations on on on graphs you know
could could be
yeah maybe also something that that's
kind of
maybe missing a bit in in kind of the
graph email setting is you know the
context where you know your your graph
is uh
your assume your graph is known
um and you know you need to have some
graph structure at least the sensible
way to construct it right but for for
many kind of more
um
I don't know like
more obviously I phrase that
um I guess for Less clearly the fine
things like okay if I'm an agent doing
perception in the real world or
something right like
if if I'm trying to create a graph of
the world you know like
um what's what's an object what do I
create what what do I create a note for
right if I want to have like one note or
object and there's some connections
between objects and things like that
just I know it's like some some wild
example
um the custom item if you actually want
to do that but let's say you want right
then there's also like all these kind of
blurry things like what's an object and
what's not an object what's kind of
somewhere in between maybe you know do
you is that a node is that so it's kind
of like I'm trying to say that the graph
structure is kind of very discreet right
like it's kind of the node is either
there is not there and Edge is there
it's not there but then the world is
kind of really fuzzy right so if if you
use graphs as a as a model for your
world then there probably has to be some
decision to be made somewhere about
these kind of fuzzy Concepts uh they
actually translate in a concrete graph
entity like an object an edge or
whatever or not uh based on you know
some kind of inference procedure
um and I don't know if we did that or
not it's kind of humorous as kind of as
intelligent agents uh but that's you
know kind of some some interesting thing
to think about maybe you could also well
maybe one way to solve that there's also
kind of stuff like soft edges and things
like that and in some way you know if
you have attention coefficients it's a
bit like that you know like if an edge
has a weight of 0.001 or something it's
almost like not being there but you know
it's still kind of there so it's uh you
know it's a bit of a soft graph
architecture uh but so I guess at the
edge level you can implement this
softness but I think it's a bit harder
at kind of the note level right like uh
how do you kind of model a node that's
kind of there and not there
um yeah
there's just some random thoughts
that's very interesting about the fuzzy
object identification and kind of
similarities and differences between
nodes and edges even though in some ways
they have some similarities too
um or interoperabilities to
one other point of contact was like
an underlying hidden space
that we understand topologically that
projects a vector space at
in from different places so that could
be a vector of thermometer readings
and we want to have a smooth path within
the homeostatic
range defined up to a boundary Point not
saying that that's the structure of the
world but a structure of a very
heuristic and simple model might be to
aim for continuity and have a defined
hid in the state space that has
continuity underneath
and is able to emit vectors so that kind
of brings some of these classifier type
discussions that you brought up and like
the kind of fundamental impossibility of
geometric classification because you you
are going to end up with gray zones
whereas even if it takes a bit wise
description you can separate the network
so that gives an actual completeness
measure
and that allows
measures like I mean amount of
computational resources or in a more
like statistically principled way like
the Bayesian information Criterion so
how many nodes should we have
we should be on some
trade-off front in some modeling space I
don't know what to tell you it's a map
not the territory and that's because
that's more justifiable and so uh even
lifelike organisms might want to self
evidence
staying emitting from a living state
and so that provides a really simple
graphical architecture to cybernetic
systems and then active inference
explores a lot of different more
specific motifs
within that broader blanket persistence
picture and the path of least action so
that's what enables the physics in that
space and why these methods which as far
as I understand are often used in
quantum mechanics
or being able to come together with
active inference this way
yeah um some something that comes to
mind when you mention this I think
there's also like a
Recent avenir research in this area
where people and it's again kind of
generated by the fact that you don't
know the graph before beforehand many
times and I think kind of the old school
approach was well you you construct it
based on some rules right like you
you're gonna say all these I don't know
some things are similar I'm going to put
an edge between them and you define
similarly in whatever where you like and
so on
um and there was this kind of recent
Trend where what you try to do is kind
of latent graph inference or some people
call it manifold learning if you think
of the graph as some sort of manifold
but this kind of very informally
speaking
and essentially what you would do is
like you would map whatever you try to
learn the raw observations
um into some latent space and that's
where you actually construct the graph
you construct the graph in the latent
space rather than kind of in in the you
know raw space so that might be kind of
a way to deal with fuzziness as well
right like because then I guess you
might lose some
some of these kind of very concrete
one-to-one mappings because you might
learn some note in the latent space that
maybe corresponds to three or four
Concepts kind of uh mixed together in
you know so there's all these kind of
nice uh experiments with neurons in the
networks kind of visualized and you know
they learn maybe a kind of a mixture of
Concepts like like if you see what
actually uh you know activates that
neuron is actually you know maybe a few
classes or different kinds of things
it's not necessarily a single thing
um
so it could be something very similar
here where you have some very entangled
um representations that are kind of
distilled in in this latent graph and
then in a way at least in concert stay
even if like kind of in the latent space
that's still like kind of a very you
know clear combinatorial structure with
respect to kind of your raw observations
um that that structure kind of can still
kind of encode the fuzziness of the
world to some degree because you have
this kind of mixture of Concepts that
got distilled in the same node or things
like that or maybe some Concepts could
be represented by multiple nodes uh
depending on you know in what you see
this Concepts there might be all sorts
of variations or concept or points of
view and so on so
um I think you know kind of latent graph
inference could be uh you know quite an
interesting way maybe to address some of
these
um issues where we were discussing
although I think uh it kind of died off
a bit in in the recent year at least as
far as I've seen there were a few you
know slightly fewer papers um on the
topic
hmm
well certainly the agents
proposed latent structure of the world
the causal structure of the world is
just map not territory and so it enables
maybe some of those core screenings
um could you go to the slide where there
was a mapping between a smooth sphere
and then a regular geometric shape
uh yeah
let's see
in this one yeah just wanted to make one
one point see if you had any um comments
at the heart of some of the
relationships that you're describing and
where you pulled back to and kind in
terms of generalization helps us
understand
this relationship between the the sphere
and the geometry
and one place that that and the
implications for data processing and all
of the computational science areas is if
you are preserving or learning or
analyzing geometry but not topology or
the other way around you might get these
different like data set aberrations like
you might have the topology of the
coffee cup but it looks like something
totally different
and so what we would really want to do
would be understand the relationship
between geometry and topology
because if we could understand it in
principle like you have it on the left
side and then in practice with the data
scheme on the right side or or insert
your own left and right side there
then we'd be able to do data
analysis in a way that respected slash
preserved
both the topology and the geometry so
it's like two compatible perspectives
that have their different like strengths
and weaknesses and heuristics and so
understanding that relationship between
geometry and topology
and the implicit
um spaces that geometry requires and so
on that has tremendous
use
and it just in closing reminds me of
Buckminster Fuller's synergetics which
uses a close packing
architecture and a tetrahedron Centric
model of coordinates
to find more continuity between surface
area and volume and between the smooth
surfaces and the great circles on them
and like the points of connectivity on
shapes so I think it's an incredibly
deep area it really has fundamental
impact inactive inference helps us think
about our models in this way kind of
like the inflated balloon and with the
fuzziness and the architecture
and the finiteness
it really brings a lot to active
inference and so I appreciate you
sharing the work with us today and
continuing to work in this way
thanks out
any last thoughts
yeah I think
um yeah what what you mentioned I think
it's been all over my thesis this kind
of tension between between topology and
and geometry and maybe what I want to
emphasize is that you know I'm not
saying kind of the the previous
perspective of looking maybe more
geometrically of things was wrong in any
way and on the contrary actually there's
lots of interesting places where these
things intersective and in kind of this
Chief uh paper I briefly went there like
if you actually read the paper there's
uh there's a lot of beautiful
intersections actually my my main
collaborative Francesco he he's a
differential geometer so
um he actually had lots of kind of
inputs from from that side and
um indeed I think you know we should try
to use all these kind of layers of
structure uh you know in the best way
possible for our methods
awesome all right thank you until next
time thanks for having me